Reducing redundant elements within our
data visualization or otherwise known as
decluttering is such an important aspect
that we dedicate an entire lesson to it
within our workshops. But we close out
that very same lesson with an important
truth that we shouldn't only declutter.
Simply decluttering and then sending our
information to our audience will still
likely have them walking away confused.
So let's take a look at this today and
first of all improve our visualization
by decluttering it. and then strengthen
it by prioritizing the main message that
we're looking to share. This visual
shows the status of work orders across
four critical asset types within an
engineering company. Along the
horizontal axis, we see each of the four
asset types and the primary left
vertical axis plots the absolute number
of orders within an asset type and those
are broken down by closed the blue bars
and open the orange bars. Finally, the
secondary vertical axis tracks the
percentage of orders closed per asset
type. The goal of this view is for our
audience to better understand which of
the individual asset areas are more
successful in closing their orders and
which might require a little bit of
attention. Now, everything that our
audience might need is present in this
view. But that's part of the problem.
What are we meant to be focusing on
here? Maybe it's the absolute number of
orders and those that have been closed.
Or maybe it's the proportion. Or indeed,
it could be both. We can begin to
improve the visual with some common
decluttering techniques like adjusting
the graph proportions, decreasing the
white space between the bars, tidying up
formatting of the axes, removing the
data labels, resizing and aligning the
chart title, and finally moving the
legend to the top as a subtitle. The
combination of these changes makes it
easier to focus on the data. But even
with these changes, it's still difficult
to make any immediate observations with
the data. And so it's at this point we
take a step back and think critically
about the main message we're looking to
share and then whether or not the graph
choices we've made help support that
message and allow it to be communicated
effectively. One way we can transition
away from the combined axes is to pull
the graphs apart vertically, leveraging
the same horizontal axis across both
views, but now with each getting its own
independent vertical axis. Having made
this change, I've noticed something off.
Lines work well for continuous data over
time, but here we're dealing with
categorical data, those asset types. In
this instance, joining the closure rates
with each asset creates a relationship
that just doesn't exist. To correct
this, I'll convert the line to
individual bars, which will better
represent this discrete, distinct data.
That's better. But something still feels
a little bit off. Maybe we're just
trying to show too much information at
once. Do we need to present all of this
data in one go? often a subset or
aggregation of the data can lead to a
much clearer final product. And so I'm
going to continue to iterate. Firstly,
I'll drop the closure rate information.
Then I'm going to switch from
positioning the closed and open bars
from their original position next to
each other to stacking them on top of
one another. Now that the order closure
rate has been removed, we can be clear
about the intention of this visual. And
displaying only the relevant data
reduces the cognitive effort required to
understand the information. But in
conversation with colleagues, we
determined that one thing our audience
cares about above all else is the
closure rate within each individual
asset type. And with that original
visual and the closure rate priority in
mind, I'm inclined to explore one final
view. And that's switching to a 100%
stack bar chart. Now clearly showing the
proportion of orders that have closed.
At this stage, I've also taken the
opportunity to switch to a horizontal
orientation to ensure the category
labels sit nicely on one single line.
Finally, I chose to order the data
series in a decreasing order of
performance. This final view allows for
immediate and accurate comparisons to be
made. And now that I've landed upon an
appropriate chart type, the final step
is to add elements that help frame and
explain the data. a goal line of 80%, an
observational takeaway to prime our
audience with the key message behind the
visual and an open question to help aid
and prompt discussion. Unlike the
original, the story now is obvious. It's
just those boiler feed water pump order
closure rates that are at an acceptable
level while all the others fall below.
Now attention can turn to remedial
conversations on how we can expedite
order closure rates in those other asset
types. Decluttering our visuals is
always a great first step. But for the
strongest communications, real success
comes from not only just sharpening
those original designs, but then
thinking critically about the message
we're looking to share and whether or
not the graph types we've selected help
support that message. Thank you very
much for watching. I hope you enjoyed
this latest data transformation video.
For more on this theme, check out our
makeovers playlist. And until next time,
thank you very much for watching and
goodbye.